{
  "reference_number": "9490",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "It is important that all goals are acheiveable and that there are intermediate goals within the overall framework"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "Zero carbon dioxoide emissions are unachievable in my view. All animals for example expel carbon dioxide as part of their metabolism.\n Humans expelling 4% in each breath. It is important to focus on significant reductios based on the WHOLE energy and carbon cycle\n\n not just a part of it. So for example Acukaldn Council pressed ahead with a household composting idea despite it being higher in\n carbon emissions. In the Uk they are going back to coal fired power stations as they have found that wood based stations result in\n higher carbon dioxide emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "It is preferable to use our our resources. Also what of the effect of the oceans in our economic zine. Surely these should be included\n\n as part of the equation as if for example someone choses to grow seaweed of particular types that are better at reducing carbon\n emissions. If forestry is to be used then the whole of life effects must be considered. Also as well as forestry- riparian panting has the\n double benefit of carbon emission control and also improvement in stream quality"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There is still unfortunately too much doggy science (regrettably often form left wing or green groups) pushing certain solutions which\n after some time have been found to be flawed because the science is unsound. Landfill methane emissions being one. There is\n virtually NO methane emissions form well run landfills as the gas is collected and burnt and bacteria readily treat the methane in the\n\n capping areas (I have proven this in many field trials)."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There needs to be some measure in place to track management of emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "There needs to be some flexibility as events, economies change and science knowledge improves, However any change needs to\n\n be with a majority of say 75% of Parliament representative members."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "See comment above"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Any consideration that involves any significant expenditure as a result of changes in climate change effects needs to be\n\nindependently verified by a group of scientists, pracgmatists and accountants before adoption. There should be no political\ninterference or addition of politically motivated topics as we cannot afford to waste time resolve the climate change issues."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "One needs a plan and programme"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Only work with reliable science and DO take the whole of life cost effects into account not just effects over the timeframe of various\nplans."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Any allocation must have an review by an independent body. Should there be a disagreement then the final decision would ride with\nthe minister."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Imperative that one has practical minded scientists; and preferably NO politically or envionmentally driven members.Namely it is all too\n\nimportant now to have highly competent people with the right unbias approach to resolve climate change issues."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "And must require a whole of life provision so that the full carbon footprint can be determined."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The functions must include regular independent reviews to ratify all substantive decisions. The committe members should be as\ncompany directors and only have tenor on an elected basis but certain role \"areas\" (such as science advisors or industry advisory).\n\nNamely people will be elected to each role area."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Often there are unintended consequences which sometimes can only be assessed if anyone can make submissions to have inputs."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Effects of Climate Change are still not well understood. There needs to be a mandatory aspect that the Committee publishes regular\n\neasy to read progress reports and publicity on progress suitable for children through to adults as it are the next few generations that\nare likely to be most seriously affected by decisions"
    }
  ]
}
